Guide to the John Spangler Nicholas Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Spangler Nicholas papers
1914-1963
MS 929
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
(33 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and research files (1914-1963) documenting the professional career and personal life of John Spangler Nicholas, a biologist and zoologist. His academic work, editorial contributions to the Journal of Experimental Zoology, and scientific research are detailed. Correspondents include: Ross Granville Harrison, Charles Rupert Stockard, and the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology.
Nicholas, John Spangler, 1893-
Conditions Governing Access
Box 19, student grades, is restricted for 75 years from date of creation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of John S. Nicholas, 1964.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1963. II. Organizations, 1918-1963. III. Yale University, 1917-1963. IV. Writings, 1914-1962. V. Research Files, 1938-1963. VI. Personal Files, 1918-1939.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and research files (1914-1963) documenting the professional career and personal life of John Spangler Nicholas, a biologist and zoologist. His academic work, editorial contributions to the Journal of Experimental Zoology, and scientific research are detailed. Correspondents include: Ross Granville Harrison, Charles Rupert Stockard, and the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology.
The Nicholas Papers are arranged in thirty-three (33) boxes and one folio, and total thirteen linear feet. The papers are arranged in the following six series:
I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1963
II. ORGANIZATIONS, 1918-1963
III. YALE UNIVERSITY, 1917-1963
IV. WRITINGS, 1914-1962
V. RESEARCH FILES, 1938-1963
VI. PERSONAL FILES, 1918-1939
SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1963, contains General and Select files of letters to and from Nicholas, primarily during his professional career as a biologist, zoologist, and editor of a scholarly journal. Correspondents include Ross Granville Harrison and Miroslava Pavlovic.
SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS, 1918-1963, contains an alphabetical arrangement of files concerning organizations, societies, associations, and bodies which Nichoals joined, supported, or was involved with in the course of his academic and professional work. This series includes material relating to Nicholas' manpower study work on behalf of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (box 6, folders 52-56), the National Research Council (boxes 8-10, folders 63-77), the National Roster of Scientific and Specialized Personnel (box 10, folders 78-82), and the United States Departments of Labor and HEW (boxes 13-14, folders 108-11).
SERIES III. YALE UNIVERSITY, 1917-1963, contains material relating to Nicholas' academic and administrative work on behalf of the Department of Zoology, the Osborn Zoological Laboratory, and the Sheffield Scientific School. Student grades and teaching files are also included in this series.
SERIES IV. WRITINGS, 1914-1962, is arranged in two sections: John S. Nicholas and Others. Nicholas files include his student notes from several courses and drafts of articles and speeches. Others files contain drafts of works by colleagues, including Ross Granville Harrison.
SERIES V. RESEARCH FILES, contains material on specific grant-funded projects Nicholas pursued and/or conducted, samples of notes, drawings, and photographs relating to amphibian and rat research and publications, and laboratory materials.
SERIES VI. PERSONAL FILES, 1918-1939, contains photographs and memorabilia of Nicholas.
A folio in Series VI contains large research charts and memorabilia.
Biographical / Historical
John S. Nicholas was born on March 10, 1893 [or 1895] in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He received his B.S. (1916) and M.S. (1917) from Pennsylvania College, and his Ph.D. from Yale University (1921). Nicholas held several academic positions at Yale University, including Bronson Professor of Comparative Anatomy (1935-1939), Sterling Professor of Biology (1939-1962), and Chairman of the Department of Zoology (1946-1956). He also served on the editorial board of the Journal of Experimental Zoology (1946-), as managing editor of the Journal (1947-), and as director of the Osborn Zoological Laboratory at Yale University (1947-). Nicholas was also a contributing member to many professional societies and organizations. He died in September, 1963 in New Haven, Connecticut.
Journal of Experimental Zoology; Biology -- Study and teaching; Science; Zoology; Biologists; Zoologists; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Greenman, Milton J. (Milton Jay), 1866-1937; Harrison, Ross G. (Ross Granville), 1870-1959; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Nicholas, John Spangler, 1893-; Stockard, Charles R. (Charles Rupert), 1879-1939; Wilson, Edmund B. (Edmund Beecher), 1856-1939; National Research Council (U.S.); United States. War Manpower Commission; Williams & Wilkins; Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology; Yale University. Dept. of Zoology; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1918-1963; Series I; 1.75 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two sections: General and Select. General consists of two sub-sections: "Chronological" and "Alphabetical." Select is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General:
    - Chronological:
      - 1918-1935, 1939-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
      - 1954-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8-16)
      - 1960-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
    - Alphabetical:
      - A-Cop, 1926-1938 (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
      - Cor-S, 1926-1938 (Box 4, Folder 24-30)
      - T-Z, 1926-1938 (Box 5, Folder 31-32)
  - Select:
    - Barron, Donald H., 1932-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 33-34)
    - Harrison, Ross Granville, 1926-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Hooker, Davenport, 1926-1956 (Box 5, Folder 36-38)
    - Lindbergh, Charles A., 1937 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Martinovitch, Peter N., 1929, 1949-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Pavlovic, Miroslava R., 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- ORGANIZATIONS, 1918-1963; Series II; 3.5 linear feet (9 boxes)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1949-1955, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - American Association of Anatomists, 1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - American Biological Society, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, 1950-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 45-46)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1948-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - American Society of Agronomy, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Bermuda Biological Station for Research, Inc., 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Biological Abstracts, 1953-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    General
    Biological Abstracts
  - Cold Spring Harbor Symposia, 1931-1935, 1953-1954, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology
    - General, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Committee on Study of Manpower Needs in the Basic Health Sciences
      - 1959-1960 November (Box 6, Folder 53)
      - 1960 December-1962 (Box 7, Folder 54-56)
  - International Institute of Embryology, 1948-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - International Society for Cell Biology, 1950-1963 (Box 7, Folder 58-59)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1941, 1949-1961, undated (Box 8, Folder 60-62)
  - National Research Council
    - Division of Biology and Agriculture, 1941-1956, undated (Box 8, Folder 63-66)
    - Office of Scientific Personnel
      - 1942-1950 1942-1950 (Box 8, Folder 67)
      - 1951-1961 1951-1961 (Box 9, Folder 68-74)
      - 1962-1963, undated 1962-1963, undated (Box 10, Folder 75-77)
  - National Roster of Scientific and Specialized Personnel
    - General
      - 1939-1942 May 1939-1942 May (Box 10, Folder 78-82)
      - 1942 June-1943, undated 1942 June-1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 83-84)
    - Code sheets, technical checklists, weekly reports, 1939-1943 (Box 11, Folder 85-90)
  - National Science Foundation, 1951-1963 (Box 12, Folder 91-92)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1941, 1947-1950 (Box 12, Folder 93)
  - New York University, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 94)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1928-1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 95)
  - Rockefeller Institute, 1955-1963 (Box 12, Folder 96)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission
    - 1953-1956 March 1953-1956 March (Box 12, Folder 97-100)
    - 1956 April-1963, undated 1956 April-1963, undated (Box 13, Folder 101-102)
  - Society of the Sigma Xi, 1934-1963, undated (Box 13, Folder 103)
  - Tissue Culture Association, 1946-1963 (Box 13, Folder 104-106)
  - United States Army, 1918-1927 (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - United States Departments of Labor and Health, Education, and Welfare: National Manpower Advisory Committee
    - 1962-1963 March 1962-1963 March (Box 13, Folder 108-109)
    - 1963 March-August 1963 March-August (Box 14, Folder 110-111)
  - University of Illinois, 1938, 1945-1947 (Box 14, Folder 112)
  - University of Michigan, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 113)
- YALE UNIVERSITY, 1917-1963; Series III; 2.75 linear feet (7 boxes)
  This series is divided into two sections: Administration and Teaching files. Administration is arranged alphabetically by name of office or department. Teaching files is arranged alphabetically by name or institution or course.
  - Administration
    - Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, Inc., 1953-1960 1953-1960 (Box 15, Folder 114)
    - Yale University
      - Miscellaneous, 1920-1963, undated (Box 15, Folder 115)
      - Committee on the Course of Study for Yale College; Committee on Educational Planning, 1940-1945, 1950, undated (Box 15, Folder 116-120)
      - Department of Zoology
        - Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 15, Folder 121)
        - Annual reports
          - 1921, 1927-1934 (Box 15, Folder 122)
          - 1935-1963, undated (Box 16, Folder 123-128)
        - Report of army courses, 1943-1944 (Box 16, Folder 129-130)
        - Miscellaneous papers, 1929-1961, undated (Box 17, Folder 131)
      - Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1950-1954 (Box 17, Folder 132)
      - Osborn Zoological Laboratory
        - Financial records, library museum, 1933-1943, 1948-1963, n.d (Box 17, Folder 133-135)
        - Vendors' correspondence, brochures, etc., 1929-1943, 1956-1961, n.d (Box 17, Folder 136-138)
      - Sheffield Scientific School
        - General
          - 1933-1942 (Box 17, Folder 139)
          - 1943-1946, undated (Box 18, Folder 140)
        - Honor students, 1934-1937, undated (Box 18, Folder 141)
        - Pre-medical students, 1927-1937, undated (Box 18, Folder 142-146)
      - Student grades, 1927-1957, undated (Box 19, Folder 147)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Student grades are restricted for 75 years from date of creation due to University policy.
  - Teaching files
    - University of Pittsburgh, 1921-1926 (Box 20, Folder 148-150)
    - Yale University
      - "Comparative Anatomy of Vertebrates,", 1930-1944, undated (Box 20, Folder 151)
      - "Embryology,", 1933-1952, undated (Box 20, Folder 152-153)
      - "General Biology,", 1917-1944, undated (Box 20, Folder 154)
      - "Vertebrate Morphology,", 1927-1928, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 155-158)
      - Miscellaneous, 1932, 1954, undated (Box 21, Folder 159-161)
      - Examinations, 1931-1951, undated (Box 22, Folder 162-164)
- WRITINGS, 1914-1962; Series IV; 3.25 linear feet (8 boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: John S. Nicholas and Others. John S. Nicholas is arranged in two sub-sections: "Student notes" and "Articles and speeches." "Student notes" is arranged chronologically under institutional headings, and alphabetically by the name of the professor. "Articles and speeches" is arranged in two sub-sub-sections: chronological and alphabetical.
  Others is arranged alphabetically by the author's name.
  - John S. Nicholas
    - Student notes
      - General, undated (Box 22, Folder 165)
      - Pennsylvania College, [ca. 1914-1917] (Box 22, Folder 166)
      - Army Medical School, Vaccine Department; George Washington University, 1915-1919 (Box 22, Folder 167)
      - Yale University
        - Boltwood, Bertram B.: "Laboratory Crafts,", undated (Box 22, Folder 168)
        - Coe, Wesley R. (Box 22, Folder 169)
          - "Genetics,", 1917-1918 (Box 22, Folder 169)
          - "Cytology,", undated (Box 22, Folder 169)
        - Detwiler, Samuel Randall: "Medical Histology,", 1919-1920 (Box 22, Folder 170)
        - Ferris, Harry B.: "Human Anatomy,", 1919-1920 (Box 23, Folder 171)
        - Harrison, Ross Granville
          - "Vertebrate Morphology,", 1917-1918 (Box 23, Folder 172)
          - "Embryology,", 1917-1918 (Box 23, Folder 173)
          - "Experimental Embryology,", 1917-1921 (Box 23, Folder 174)
        - Kirkham, William B.
          - "Histology,", 1917-1918 (Box 23, Folder 175)
          - "Comparative Anatomy,", 1918 (Box 23, Folder 175)
        - Laurens, Henry
          - "Comparative Physiology,", 1919-1920 (Box 23, Folder 176)
          - "General Physiology,", 1920-1921 (Box 23, Folder 176)
        - Petrunkevitch, Alexander: "Invertebrate Morphology,", 1917-1918 (Box 24, Folder 177)
        - Underhill, Frank P.: "Physiological Chemistry,", 1918 (Box 24, Folder 178)
        - Woodruff, Lorande L.
          - "History of Biology,", 1917-1918 (Box 24, Folder 179)
          - "Biology of the Protozoa,", 1919-1920 (Box 24, Folder 179)
        - Research, undated (Box 24, Folder 180)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 24, Folder 181-182)
        - Woods Hole
          - Calkins, G.N.: "Protozoology,", 1919 (Box 24, Folder 183)
          - "Invertebrate Zoology, 1919 (Box 24, Folder 184)
    - Articles and speeches
      - 1920-1934 (Box 25, Folder 185-204)
      - 1934-1948 (Box 26, Folder 205-224)
      - 1948-1952, 1959-1962, undated (Box 27, Folder 225-257)
      - undated (Box 28, Folder 258-263)
      - Fragments, undated (Box 28, Folder 264)
      - Abstracts and reprints, 1921-1937, undated (Box 28, Folder 265)
      - Biographical sketches
        - Detwiler, Samuel Randall, 1957-1959 (Box 28, Folder 266-267)
        - Harrison, Ross Granville, 1956-1961, undated (Box 28, Folder 268-271)
  - Others
    - Defrise, A., 1933 (Box 29, Folder 272)
    - Harrison, Ross Granville, 1918, 1921, undated (Box 29, Folder 273)
    - Lang, Margaret E., 1958-1959 (Box 29, Folder 274)
    - Oppenheimer, Jane, 1941, 1955-1958, undated (Box 29, Folder 275)
    - Polezhajev, L.W., 1945, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 276)
    - Miscellaneous: A-Z, 1918-1960, undated (Box 29, Folder 277-279)
- RESEARCH FILES, 1938-1963; Series V; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series is divided into three sections: Grant materials; Notes, Drawings, and Photographs; and Laboratory materials. Grant materials is arranged alphabetically by funding agency. Notes, drawings, and photographs is arranged under the headings: "Amphibians," "Rats," and "Miscellaneous." Laboratory materials occupies a single folder.
  - Grant materials
    - American Cancer Society, 1946-1959, undated (Box 30, Folder 280-284)
    - National Science Foundation, 1949-1963 (Box 30, Folder 285-286)
    - Yale University, 1938-1940, 1956-1959, undated (Box 30, Folder 287)
  - Notes, drawings, photographs, undated
    - Amphibians (Box 30, Folder 288)
    - Amphibians (Box 31, Folder 289-294)
    - Amphibians, rats (Box 32, Folder 295)
    - Rats (Box 32, Folder 296-301)
      See also: box 34, folder 307
    - Miscellaneous (Box 33, Folder 302-303)
  - Laboratory materials, undated (Box 33, Folder 304)
- PERSONAL FILES, 1918-1939; Series VI; .5 linear feet (1 box, 1 folio)
  This series is divided into two sections, Photographs and Memorabilia. Each is arranged chronologically.
  - Photographs, 1926-1939, undated (Box 33, Folder 305)
  - Memorabilia, 1918-1931, undated (Box 33, Folder 306)
    See also: box 34, folder 308
  - Oversize (Folio)
    - Rat chart, undated (Box 34, Folder 307)
    - Memorabilia, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 308)